A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Corporation, Treasurer and Assistant Treasurer, Administrative Correspondence FA865
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Corporation, Treasurer and Assistant Treasurer, Administrative Correspondence
1910-1954 April
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Gates, Frederick Taylor
FA865
0.88 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
2 boxes.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence with Business Manager and Bursar. Includes statements of the income account of the Institute during coming fiscal year. Much of the correspondence in the early years deals with construction costs and results from the fact that the Institute's growth constantly outstripped bookkeeping methods. Includes requests and letters of transmittal of checks from Treasurer for Institute's current expenses. Later correspondence is mostly letters of transmittal and acknowledgement, including financial reports and budgets for the operation of the Treasurer's office. Includes also assessed valuations and tax exemptions for a number of years and some estimates of income. Some copies of minute from the Finance Committee.
Arrangement
Chronological.
Biographical / Historical
By the By-Laws of the Corporation adopted in 1910, a Treasurer of the Corporation was to be elected by the Board of Trustees at the annual meeting. The Treasurer was designated as the officer to have custody of the permanent funds and securities of the Corporation, to pay bills incurred by resolution of the Board of Trustees under the authority of the Executive Committee, and to make payments to the Board of Scientific Directors upon authorized requisition from them. It was the duty of the Treasurer to keep proper books, to present at each meeting an exact accounting of receipts and disbursements and to present an annual report of the accounts of the year. Additions to the Rules of the Board of Trustees provided that the Treasurer act as secretary of. the Finance Committee and have custody, of its minutes and other papers and documents relating to the work of the committee.
The first treasurer of the Corporation was Louis Guerineau Myers who served until 1932. Costs of the Treasurer's office were shared among several of the Rockefeller philanthropic enterprises such as the General Education Fund and the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Fund. The Board of Trustees was empowered to appoint an Assistant Treasurer and Lefferts Mason Dashiell was appointed in 1923. He became Acting Treasurer in 1932 upon the death of Louis G. Myers and was appointed Treasurer of the Corporation in 1939. Edward Robinson became Assistant Treasurer and Treasurer in 1939 with Benson Blake as Assistant Treasurer. In 1942 Edward Emerson became Assistant Treasurer and in 1954 he was succeeded by Robert Letort.
In 1953 new By-Laws of the Corporation were adopted, and under the reorganization then instituted a complete study of the business and financial administration of the Institute was authorized. Over a period of several years thoroughgoing changes of positions and responsibilities were established.
Between 1955-1959 Edward Robinson served as Treasurer and Robert Letort as Assistant Treasurer. Lindsley F. Kimball became Treasurer April 1959 (though elected to take office January 1, 1959) and William E. Dietz took office as Assistant Treasurer in March 1959. The office of William Dietz was enlarged to include the newly created office of Comptroller which included supervision of the office of the Bursar which in 1961 became the Bursar and Deputy Assistant Treasurer.
In May 1965 when Lindsley F. Kimball retired, J. Richardson Dilworth, who as Trustee had been very active and influential on the Finance Committee became Treasurer. Until 1969, while new patterns were developing, William E. Dietz, as Assistant Treasurer and Controller supervised much of the financial management of the University. William E. Dietz retired December 1969.
Finally a clear-cut division between the management of the University's business and the management of financial properties and investments was established. Joseph Richardson Dilworth served as Treasurer, Sydney Anglin Woodd-Cahusac as Associate Treasurer and Arthur Francis Hubbard as Deputy Assistant Treasurer. In May 1971 J. Richardson Dilworth, who continued as a trustee of the University and chairman of its Finance Committee was succeeded as Treasurer by Sydney A. Woodd-Cahusac and in 1972 Arthur F. Hubbard became Assistant Treasurer.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 190
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for scholarly research.
Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Gates, Frederick Taylor
- 1910-1935 (Box 1)
  - Non-routine items include (Box 1)
    - Accountant's report of Dr. Carrel's credit account for temporary Hospital at Compiègne, 1917 February 7 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence relating to Foundation grant for War Relief and Research, 1917 (Box 1)
    - Covering letter to E.B. Smith and copy of letter sent to John d. Rockefeller expressing appreciation for grant, 1920 July 24 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence dealing with coverage for insurance against fire risk, 1921 August (Box 1)
    - Report from E.M. Smillie on conditions at Clyde Farm, 1929 December 10 (Box 1)
    - Handwritten note to Simon Flexner from Mrs. Myers expressing thanks for expression of sympathy at death of L.G. Myers, 1932 February 9 (Box 1)
    - Memorial minute read at Corporation meeting at death of L.G. Myers, 1932 October 28 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence regarding mortgage on farm at Clyde, 1933 December (Box 1)
    - Outline of financial accounting procedure at RIMR, 1934 October 26 (Box 1)
- 1936-1954 (Box 2)
  - Non-routine items include (Box 2)
    - Copy of letter from Squires and Co. in regard to treatment and disposition of premiums and discounts, 1938 April 14 (Box 2)
    - Memorial minute in honor of Lefferts Mason Dashiell as sent to Mrs. Dashiell and acknowledgment, 1938 June 30 (Box 2)
      Scope and Contents note
      Also includes newspaper notice of death on February 28, 1938.
    - To Trustees of Institute from Edward Robinson explaining projected plan to adopt accounting procedures 'recommended by Squires and Co. that securities value on books be carried at original cost', 1941 May 2 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence regarding removal of papers of historical interest from Chase National Bank to Institute's safe, 1942 February 17 (Box 2)
    - Copy of suggested simplified form of balance sheet that can be made public, 1944 May 9 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence regarding practice of entering authorizations before disbursements are made, 1946 October 18 (Box 2)
    - Copy of new Workmen's Compensation Board regulations regarding self-insurance security deposit, 1947 February 5 (Box 2)
    - Compilation from Minute Books and Manager's Annual Reports of operating and construction expenses of Institute 1901-1917/18 as requested by Mr. Fosdick, 1949 February 10 (Box 2)
    - Salary scale as compiled by Edward Emerson, 1949 May 6 (Box 2)
    - Copy of Bursar's statement of Receipts and Disbursements July 1951-June 1952 and Valuation schedule with group of supporting schedules, 1952 September 2 (Box 2)